[Music]
gabble mate' is a world-famous expert on
addiction in his book in the realm of
hungry ghosts he talks about how
addiction is best viewed not as a crime
or an illness but as a coping mechanism
for a personal spiritual crisis
addiction is a response to human
suffering it's an attempt of a human
being to feel actually normal and so
rather than a disease or a choice it
really is a coping mechanism social
media there's been a lot in the press
around our addiction to social media so
what do you feel drives that are our
unhealthy relationship with it because
of the same dynamics there's more to it
well you can use social media
responsibly just you can exercise
responsibly or you can exercise
addictively or you can use social media
effectively so stay internal
relationship to them these activities
that defines whether addictive or not
now if you're using something for
temporary relief for pain pain relief or
pleasure and you crave it despite
negative consequences you were an
addiction whereas if you're using social
media not to escape the emotional
distress not because you're craving it
but something because it's a useful
modality and you don't suffer negative
consequences then it's not an addiction
so it's not the external behavior I mean
you can drink alcohol not addictively
you can have sex not effectively you can
go shopping monitor activity or you can
engage in all the activities in a purely
compulsive addictive fashion depending
what the internal automatic dynamic is
does it provide temporary pleasure pain
relief do you crave it and you continue
with that despite negative consequences
that's what toys whether it's an
addiction now broadly speaking social
media are highly addictive and a lot of
people addicted and then having a
devastating effects on their lives but
not of course everybody especially on
social media or just in general we that
this polarization seems to be
increasingly ideological you mentioned
people are
really in their specific tribes and
speaking from you know let's have a
chance to hit the other tribe
okay can we be a dictatorial adji well
again if you define addiction as I do as
any behavior that a person craves finds
temporary pleasure or relief and suffers
negative consequences and cannot give up
despite negative consequences that's an
addiction
again I don't care whether it's sex
gambling ideology or cocaine and and the
brain circuits are the same the same
brain circuits are involved in all the
addictions so we think there's all these
different addictions if you actually
look at the addicted brain it's the same
brain circuitry that's involved in all
addictions so an ideology that allows
you free expression of the impulses you
will get to hit somebody if you're angry
get it through a window to a rock
through somebody's window or a verbal
bombed to their personal sense of self
if it if you're lacking a sense of
personal power but the ideology gives
you a pseudo environment may belong to
something really important if there's no
meaning in your life and the etiology
gives you a pseudo meaning if you're
lacking genuine pleasure in your life
and you get the pseudo pleasure of
connecting with people who see things
the same way an etiology can function
like an addiction and furthermore it
invites denial it's just like addiction
of is the right so now when I was in my
addicted behavior which I have been I
was in total denial that was an addict
to me was just a natural thing to do it
doesn't matter what the cost was to the
people are on me hey doggies can do the
same thing you're in total denial about
the impact on yourself or on others so
yeah it is you can function like an
addiction and you mentioned the the word
meaning which really is is the word
that's come up a lot with a lot of our
guests and you know there's there's a
sense that what we're seeing now with
the increased polarization the chaos and
world Paulette
is driven in large part by a spiritual
void a loss of connection and meaning I
remember in the book as well you
mentioned that's an aspect of drug
addiction as well would you agree with
that general sense that we are facing a
global maybe void in meaning well
there's an American psychologist who had
the human beings are all creatures with
special needs and I think one of our
special needs is for meaning our lives
are not meant to be just lived for the
daily sake of physical existence now
that meaning in a tribal setting is
automatically provided for you because
you're bigger than yourself and you
belong to something greater than
yourself and when you're connected with
nature
you're connected with some spiritual
practice or belief you have some meaning
that transcends your daily struggles for
survival of a society as feelings reduce
stuff like we talked about meeting a lot
and we talked about broad values such as
freedom and democracy and so on
but that's not what people experience in
their daily lives nobody experiences
democracy in our lives mostly people
work in institutions we're told what to
do and they had no voice in a matter
whatsoever
and the freedom is really used to making
choices in meaningless alternatives so
there's a deep and and as more more
disconnection as we've already mentioned
so there's there's a deep lack of
meaning in people's lives the addictions
can actually certainly come along and
provide a false temporary but
momentarily satisfactory sense of
meaning and meaning is is important to
all of us we all want to feel there's
something more significant about our
lives than simply the fact that we have
dinner and evening and we
in the morning on that point around this
devastating effect we've talked a lot on
the channel and some of our guests have
talked about that what feels like an
increasingly polarized world you know
the people are very entrenched in camps
particularly on social media and you
know we've also talked around how we get
trapped in kind of fight or flight I
suspect I know social media seems like a
very reactive space we seem to behave
differently on there so it's curious can
you can your work also help us kind of
get an understanding of that a broader
understanding of how we behave on social
media well first of all what's the case
in this society is that people are less
than as connected human beings were not
meant to live in these from the
evolutionary point of view we're not
designed to live in these complex vast
aggregations were meant to live in small
hunter band
hunter-gatherer bands where everybody
knows everybody else and there's a deep
connection in between people and that's
how we've lived for the most part for
millions of years hundreds of thousands
tens of thousands of years of evolution
until really quite recently there's a
lot of disconnect in in society people
that literally don't know their
neighbors neighborhoods are no longer
neighborhoods they're isolated domiciles
for the most part which means is a deep
hunger for connection and the social
media provides a simulacrum of
connection the pretense of connection
and so what do people have on social
media they have friends they like each
other
these are attachment dynamics these are
connection dynamics but the friends
aren't real friends cause real friends
know you and you're not afraid to show
them who you are on social media people
have concocted an artificially adorned
persona and it's these artificial
entities that then people like so the
individual never gets the sense of being
really liked because they know that it's
just an image that's being liked and and
the so-called friends are not there for
you when you need them and you'd use the
same language liking and friends are
very strong language but social media is
a pale
so the less it meets your real needs the
more addictive it is because the more
more what you need to get number one
number two I'm not sure that it's caused
but it certainly revealed the many
subcultures in the society and allows
people who belong to various ideological
groupings to identify one another and to
band together and to have sort of a
pseudo camaraderie so we can all hate
the same thing we can all be hostile to
the same people and anybody can express
an opinion in the old days of
newsletters to the newspapers people
have to repeat irresponsible what they
wrote they had to identify themselves
social media you can say anything you
want about anybody doesn't matter
hurtful or wrong hateful really and not
even identify yourself so it allows
people who otherwise are on the margins
of society to aggregate in these pseudo
groups that then promote one another's
most negative tendencies and there's no
good guidance there there's no
leadership there's nobody to call you to
your senses there's nobody to say really
do you really mean that is that what you
really intend what's really going on so
there's peer groupings without any kind
of guidance it's really like a teenage
gang phenomenon where people band
together mostly for negative reasons
they're lacking contact so they need to
band together so that's legitimate but
they they get they band together without
mentorship without tradition without
adult guidance and so we see what we see
yeah and so is you feeling that in those
groups specially if there's a lot of
hateful rhetoric in it
what would be your kind of immediate
sense of what a way through that would
be or a way to reach those people well I
don't know that there's a way to reach
those people except to a personal
contact I think that
[Music]
should take the analogy of the teenage
gang only if somebody comes along who
can provide genuine guidance that these
people will trust but with the social
media groups who knows where they live
who knows how to contact them
individually who knows how to speak to
them in a way that's compassionate and
enrolling at the same time that'll open
up a different parts of themselves so
but I don't know that the social media
causes all that or simply reinforces it
or maybe makes it more manifest I think
you've always had these bookings
they just haven't found a way to at
least evolves that such people they just
haven't found a way to reinforce and
validate so they're quite at the same
degree as you have it now yeah I was
very interested reading in the book you
use the example if there's an area of
the brain called the OFC yeah and that's
kind of it mediates in part it picks up
on physical emotional cues and that's a
big part of how we trust each other and
as I was reading it I was thinking well
that's something we certainly can't do
online and can only happen face-to-face
and so yeah it sounds like to have these
authentic conversations we need to be in
contact well you see the as you and I
are speaking to each other early uh
we're tracking each other's face and and
our ear muscles are actually adjusting
themselves automatically to hear not
just what's being said but also the tone
of voice image being said and you will
nod when I say something or I might nod
or smile when you say something so
communication is as much about these
nonverbal cues which are meeting it to a
nervous nervous system as it is about
the verbal content now none of that
exists on social media it's not genuine
communication human communication is
almost mentally face-to-face and
even if I would a lot write a letter to
somebody that was gonna mail that's a
much more conscious and deliberate
process than dashing something of a
social media and pushing the send button
in a state of tizzy you know so that
it's much less impulsive so social media
really takes away the the nuts and bolts
of human communication and provides only
the surface manifestation of it
so what masquerade as communication is
really diatribes very often and I know
what it's like because I get an email
and which might trigger me and then
right away I want to write it out and
then push the send button and boy have I
had to learn not to do that because
there's no reflection there just
whatever emotion arises you express it
and then you communicate it right away
without any reflection if I'm talking to
somebody as long as we're connected by
and large I'm going to reflect on what I
say before I say it by and large I'm
going to be modulated by the fact that
I'm talking to a real human being and is
that point in my book the what the
addicts lack very often is emotional
self-regulation they they they the parts
of the brain had regulator emotions
including me orbital frontal cortex just
don't develop and addicted people
because the conditions for development
are adequate so the brain does develop
an interaction at the environment so
they have a lot of people with brains
that are not fully developed there might
be intellectually adult but the
emotional circuits aren't so now you
have a lot of people with emotional
under development communicating
impulsively on social media and that's
what we're saying and so people will say
horrible things of social media that
might not they might never even say in a
real person agreement
a lot of the understanding that's in the
book has come from working with with
people in states of distress working
with individuals how do you see that as
being applied more widely to society do
you think that we have a crisis with
with the same issues that people are
struggling with individually in society
and if so how do we deal with that well
in in the book in the realm of novels I
pointed out that addiction is rooted in
trauma now then I look at society as a
whole and if society let's look at
British society or American society were
to be seen as an individual how would we
see these individuals as beginning when
I look at the the two individuals that
ran for the presidents of the US are
both deeply traumatized people one of
them so much' says that the world is a
horrible place those are his words that
sense of the world's horror arose from
his Rea dysfunctional childhood where he
was demeaned and attacked and humiliated
by his father
one of the brothers dragged himself to
death really traumatized person and a
Tomasulo penis impulsivity is lack of
attention in his emotional shut down in
his ex activity in his paranoia the
person who ran against him was an
emotionally shut down person who learned
from her mother very early that she
mustn't be vulnerable
they literally told the story about that
during a convention how the mother
basically tells her you mustn't be
afraid you mustn't let me have be
vulnerable this person then as pneumonia
without even telling the world about it
during the election campaign this a
person puts up with the philandering
'he's of a highly immoral husband and
protects it that's a sign of emotional
shutdown in trauma so you had to
traumatize individuals running for the
presidency of the most popular I should
say the most
powerful nation on earth that means it's
a traumatized society they had a choice
of in two kinds of dramas are we getting
further and further into that realm of
hungry ghosts well none of us is a
Buddhist image where there are several
realms as the animal realm of our age
and our appetites and our lusts the
human realm with the ordinary selves the
hell realm with actually the animal
realm is actually our drives in our
lusts the human realm is ordinary selves
the hell realm is the unbearable
emotions of hatred and rage and loathing
and terror and so on
there's a couple of other realms no the
hungry ghosts roam the creatures are
depicted as ones with large empty
bellies insatiable got got guts small
narrow of gullets and small mouths so
they can never get enough from the
outside always trying to feed themselves
in other words they're always buying the
products of this consumer society always
trying to fill themselves with more fame
more food more fantasy more Goods and my
contention is is that we dwell so many
of us and I endorse Trump as our attempt
to escape the Haram there's emotions in
us we can't stand we try and stuff them
down with consumables with drugs with
behaviors with social attainment with
social approval with meaningless
activities so yes this is society of
hungry ghosts where people are by and
large alone they haunt our lives without
being fully engaged and their insatiable
and their insatiable insatiability then
finds its cultural expression on
television you have a food channel not
just all about eating nothing wrong with
eating but this but this cultural
obsession what is that a substitute for
and you talked before about the the
realm of the hungry ghosts and that's a
Buddhist metaphor do you find the
Jungian framework to be useful the idea
of the shadow and integration of the
shadow in this work well we all have our
shadow side
which has to be integrated I mean
there's a part of me that's full of rage
and hatred and jealousy and envy and
sometimes homicidal fantasies that's
just a part of me nothing wrong with
that
as long as I'm aware that they're in me
and they're not me
my problem with unionism however is that
it ascribes these qualities to the
shadow side to sing over an archetypical
thing they don't talk about Toronto very
much whereas I think ins were pointed in
my book in irrelevant of course is that
these dark impulses and people and the
need to escape from them actually arise
a little genuine human experience
they're not simply part of human nature
they're really outcomes of trauma and
that trauma is experienced in a
childhood and in my view unless you deal
with the trauma you're not really
dealing with the shadow side it's one
thing to acknowledge those titles that
it's there but if you look at that
unless you look at a traumatic basis of
it so I do think that Freudianism and
even unionism unity is much more
sophisticated I think than fighters and
has much more meaningful things to say
about the human functioning for all the
great insights that they both had and I
learned a lot from both but they both
ignored trauma and I think the trauma is
the missing piece in modern psychology
and modern education modern medicine and
so I think that without looking at
trauma speaking of the shadow side
remains somewhat shallow and you're
you're from Canada yeah one of the the
biggest phenomenon of the last couple of
years has been Jordan Peterson yeah what
have you made of him his rise and what
it says about the culture that people
are so thirsting for what he's talking
about
Peterson first was very bright
extraordinaire tick youlet and in some
ways a compelling speaker so he said
he's an attractive figure in some ways
when I read him I sense a lot of
suppressed rage in him in fact I think
his voice is choking with a rage alot of
time
it's anything if he talks about rage
that he have to deal with it I don't
think you'll understand just angry yet
and it's and if you look at his websites
the comments were full of rage by his
young acolytes
now that's an energetic thing it's his
energy that draws people as much as what
he actually teaches secondly he teaches
a repression I mean he he very rightly
takes an issue where somebody mandates
the cencon language and he very rightly
and righteously since above all not be
dictated to about what language I'm
gonna use well good for him I'm on favor
of not mandating language on one hand on
the other hand he basically advocates
repression in his book he talks about
how an angry to your child needs to be
sit by themselves until they get over it
rather than understanding why a child
would be angry rage - what frustrations
are having and what human contact they
need to help them move through that
anger he says repress the anger so he's
all about repressed anger for example
circuit and it's very interesting when
he talks about children you have some
little varmints and little monsters and
so on I know that's meant to be humorous
but it's also certain way of thinking of
the young human child so fundamentally I
steam as an agent of repression he
posing as an agent of libertarianism not
to mention he's got this big in his
bonnet about what he considers to be
seems to consider to be conspiracies by
left-wing intellectuals they seem to be
his Buettner are being a left-wing
intellectual myself I'd like to talk to
him so now what were you so upset about
Jordan what are you so afraid of you
know he talks about these bloody
Marxists and and any any points are very
accurately
all the horror that occurred under
so-called Marxist regimes particularly
in the Soviet Union
he's absolutely accurate about that but
then he promotes Christianity shall I
tell him about the mass murders that
occurred in the name of Christianity
should I tell him about all the millions
that were slaughtered in the names of
the gentle Jesus in other words let's be
fair about it he seems to pick
ideologies to attack and abhor and
embrace other ideologies that are just
as murderers in practice sometimes it's
a much more interesting question for me
what happened in Eastern Europe how come
under an ideology it was meant to be
liberate people so many people were
oppressed I come from Eastern Europe I
was born in Hungary he doesn't have to
tell me about what was like but how
about asking how come a religious
philosophy that was meant to promote
love and acceptance and compassion has
become such an agent of two million a of
repression oppression and
and-and-and-and-and killing so can we be
objective or we're gonna be simply
tribal about it I have a lot to say to
Jordan or a lot to as much as I
appreciate actually some of what he says
and as interesting as I find them I
think is a very mixed figure largely an
occasion to of repression
[Music]
you